A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Public Broadcasting, Office Files of Richard Catalano FA1517
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Public Broadcasting, Office Files of Richard Catalano
1962-1968
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1517
1.99 Cubic Feet 4 LTR size and 1 LGL size Hollinger boxes
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the staff subject files of Richard Catalano who held a number of different positions at the Ford Foundation. Between 1963 and 1969, Catalano served as an Assistant to the Secretary, a Program Officer in International Affairs, and a Program Officer in the Office of Public Broadcasting. All of the material in the collection pertains to Catalano's time as Program Officer in the Office of Public Broadcasting. These records comprise one series that documents the Foundation's support for educational television (ETV) in the 1960s and its submission to the Federal Communications Commission (FCC) in 1966 that proposed the creation of a satellite system to serve both noncommercial television (informational, cultural, and instructional) and commercial television.
Many of the files appear to hold materials maintained and organized by Catalano rather than materials that directly regard his own activities. The small amount of correspondence authored by or addressed to Catalano found within the collection is all dated 1967 or later. By containing records created through the work of other Ford Foundation officers like Howard Dressner, the collection documents a larger history of the Foundation's Satellite Project and ETV efforts.
In addition to correspondence, the collection holds papers, drafts, notes, memoranda, speech transcripts, brochures, and publications.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers' papers were transferred to, and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:020.
Arrangement
Collection consists of one series. That series is comprised of subject files related to the Ford Foundation Office of Public Broadcasting's work in educational television and the Satellite Project. The subject files are ordered in an inconsistent alphabetical arrangement.
Original order was maintained as much possible.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Educational television (ETV)/Satellite Project subject files, 1962-1968
Biographical / Historical
Richard Catalano (1934-2007) held a number of different positions at the Ford Foundation. Between 1963 and 1969, Catalano served as an Assistant to the Secretary, a Program Officer in International Affairs, and a Program Officer in the Office of Public Broadcasting. After he left the Office of Public Broadcasting in 1969, he briefly continued in public television-related work with positions as Vice President for Administration at National Educational Television (NET) and Vice President for Media Services at the Educational Broadcasting Corporation.
Catalano was born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. After he graduated from Bowdoin College in 1955, he served in the United States Army in Korea from between 1956 and 1958. He received a Master's Degree from the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy at Tufts University in the year he left the army, and then, in 1963, he earned a J.D. from George Washington University.
Catalano's later career involved a variety of administrative positons at higher education institutions such as the School of Law at Pace University and the City University of New York.
Other Finding Aids
Finding aids concerning the the Ford Foundation Satellite Project include:
FA1518 Ford Foundation records, Public Broadcasting, Satellite Project
Finding aids concerning Richard Catalano's work in International Affairs include:
FA748 Ford Foundation records, International Affairs records
- Educational television (ETV)/Satellite Project subject files, 1962-1968; 1; 1.99 Cubic Feet 4 LTR and 1 LGL size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains a set of subject files Richard Catalano maintained to document the Ford Foundation's support for educational television (ETV) in the 1960s and its submission to the Federal Communications Commission (FCC) in August 1966 that proposed the creation of a satellite system to serve both noncommercial and commercial television. The majority of the records in the series document the larger scope of the Ford Foundation's Satellite Project and ETV efforts done through the work of officers and executives like Howard Dressner and McGeorge Bundy rather than merely document the work in which Catalano was directly involved. Dates on correspondence authored by and addressed to Catalano suggest that he did not participate in the initiatives of the Office for Public Broadcasting until 1967. Much of Catalano's activities concerned grant requests for educational television related projects.
  In addition to correspondence between the Ford Foundation and potential grantees, the series also contains correspondence between the Foundation and organizations that shared similar interests in the FCC's proceeding on domestic satellite systems. Other aspects of the Foundation's Satellite Project are documented in the series by the letters the Foundation sent to the FCC in relation to its submitted proposal, consultant reports for a prototype satellite, and a summary of the Foundation's role in the proceeding and other related events. Furthermore, the Ford Foundation's public relations work for the Satellite Project and other ETV activities are documented by transcripts of various speeches and interviews.
  A number of files in the series regard the work of Charles A. Siepmann. The Ford Foundation hired him as a consultant to review informational programming by National Educational Television (NET) and the Public Broadcasting Laboratory (PBL).
  - ABC, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Telephone and Telegraph Company, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - A - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Augenstein report, Institute for Defense Analysis (IDA), 1966 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Banzhaf, John F., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bass, Milton - I Was an Educational TV Dropout paper, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Blank, David - CBS, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Codel, Edward - Domestic Communications Satellites: How They Will Affect Local Broadcasts address to Tennessee Broadcasters Association, 1966 October (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - CBS, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Columbia University project - Grant request, $250,000, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Commerce, U.S. Department of, press release, 1966 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cooney, Thomas E. - Enrico Fermi film, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Culkin, Reverend John - Broadcast Communications: Past, Present and Future address American Management Association (AMA) Conference on Educational Technology, 1966 August 11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - C - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Defense, U.S. Department of, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dirlam-Kahn memorandum, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - D - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Educational Television Network Demonstration Project report by Gunn, Kiermaier, Kraetzer, and McCarter, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - National Education Television (NET) - French TV project/Office De Radiodiffusion-Television Francaise (ORTF) - Future international telecommunication, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Format for typing Federal Communications Commission (FCC) submission, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Broadcasters Nonprofit Satellite Service (BNS) fact sheet, 1966 September (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - E - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Employment requests, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Ewald, William - The Next 50 Years conference, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - European Broadcasting Union (EBU), 1966 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - F - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Grossman, Lawrence, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - G - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - The Hagerstown ETV Experiment--10 Years After memo - Eugene Staples, 1966 September 27 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Harris, Lou - Model election projection, 1967 August 14 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Hughes Aircraft Company, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
  - Letters to Federal Communications Commission (FCC) Commissioners, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Federal Communications Commission (FCC) - List of people who received December submission, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Federal Communications Commission (FCC) submission - August and December 1966 mailing lists, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Internal Broadcast Institute (IBI), 1966 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - IBM, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - H - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Replies to people submitting ideas and proposals, 1966-1967; File contains a music recording of songs by musician Leo Ross. Ross submitted a proposal to the Ford Foundation about showing films from foreign countries and songs from amateur musicians on public television. (Box 3, Folder 39-41)
  - Leo Ross music recording: "Love is King" and "Somebody's Soldier", undated; Sound, 6 minutes; 45 RPM record (Box T1, Reel 1)
    This music recording was found with Leo Ross' proposal to the Ford Foundation for showing films from foreign countries and songs from amateur musicians on public television.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Inquiry: Implications for Televised Instruction publication, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - The Informational and Cultural Services - Howard Dressner paper, draft, 1966 July 21 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Space Applications Summer Study: Broadcast Satellites - National Academy of Sciences, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 44-45)
  - Ende, Asher - Deputy Director of the Common Carrier Bureau, Federal Communications Commission (FCC), 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Bundy, McGeorge - Remarks to the American Society of Newspaper Editors: Reading It More and Enjoying It Less, 1967 April 20 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Bundy, McGeorge - Channel 13 interview, 1966 December 12 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Bundy, McGeorge - Channel 13 interview, 1966 August 1 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Bundy, McGeorge - Address before National Association of Educational Broadcasters (NAEB), 1967 March (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Bundy, McGeorge - Federal Communications Commission (FCC) submission letter, 1967 September 18 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Bundy, McGeorge - Federal Communications Commission (FCC) submission letter, 1966 December 12 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Bundy, McGeorge - Federal Communications Commission (FCC) submission letter, 1966 August 1 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Bundy, McGeorge - Federal Communications Commission (FCC) submission letter, 1967 April 3 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Bundy, McGeorge - Press conference, 1966 August 1 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Bundy, McGeorge - National Urban League speech, 1966 August 2 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Bundy, McGeorge - Speech delivered to the University Club, 1966 December 3 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Bundy, McGeorge - Senate statement, 1966 August 17 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Bundy, McGeorge - Senate statement, 1967 April 12 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Bundy, McGeorge - Bundy, Friendly, and Ginsburg testimony to House Committee on Interstate and Foreign Commerce, 1967 July (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Douglas proposal correspondence, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Bundy, McGeorge - Addresses, general, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Douglas - Space Research Vehicle: Technical Proposal, 1967 June (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Satellite - Summary of Ford Foundation role in Federal Communications Commission (FCC) satellite proceeding and related developments, 1967 December (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Siepmann, Charles A. - National Educational Television (NET) consultant, 1962-1968 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Siepmann, Charles A. - Weekly reports, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Siepmann, Charles A. - Quarterly reports, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Siepmann, Charles A. - Annual reports, circa 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Siepmann, Charles A. - Educational Radio and the Public Interest report, 1967 July (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Speeches on National Educational Television (NET) and educational television (ETV), 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - State ETV Legislation Survey, 1962-1966 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - State University of New York (Sam Gould), 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Telecommunications Management, Office of - Executive Office of the President, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Television Information Office (TIO), 1967 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - United Church of Christ - Action before Federal Communications Commission (FCC) regarding TV coverage of Negroes, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - WBAI (Radio) Pacifica, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Yale University educational television (ETV) proposal, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 77)